A Guide to the Helen M. Anderson Papers, 1818-1912
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
Helen M. Anderson Papers, 1818-1912.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 89.13
24 items.
Helen M. Anderson.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1989.
Biographical/Historical Information
Helen M. Anderson was a resident of Williamsburg, Va. during the Civil War.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence mostly between Helen M. Anderson and U. S. Army officers occupying Williamsburg during the Civil War in 1862. Papers document the seizure of wine from Mrs. Anderson's house, its storage at the Eastern State Insane Asylum, Anderson's attempts to retrieve the wine, and the ultimate dispensing of the wine by the provost marshall. Correspondents include Lt. John Simpson, Lt. Col. S. E. Smith, and Capt. Flanagan of the 5th Pennsylvania Cavalry Regiment. Also included are the will of Sarah (Mrs. Francis) Jerdone (1818), the will of Robert S. Bright (1912) and an autobiographical essay by Robert A. Bright (born in 1839 in Williamsburg).
Arrangement
Chronologically arranged.
Index Terms
Persons:
Anderson, Helen M.; Bright, Robert S., d. ca. 1912.; Bright, Robert A., b. 1839.; Simpson, John.; Smith, S. E.
Subjects:
Wine and wine making--Virginia--Williamsburg.
Corporate Names:
Eastern State Hospital (Va.); United States--Army--Pennsylvania Cavalry Regiment, 5th (1861-1865)
Geographical Names:
Williamsburg (Va.)--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History-- Civil War, 1861-1865--Occupied territories.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Confiscations and contributions.
Contents List
- Will of Sarah (Mrs. Francis) Jerdone, Louisa County. (Official copy) 4 pp, 28 December 1818.
- Request for protection. Helen Maxwell Anderson, Williamsburg, to General George McClellan. Reply from D. Jameson, 6 May 1862.
- Letter to certify house search and safe [house] guard for Mrs. [Helen M.] Anderson. By order of Lt. Col. Smith and Lt. W. J. Simpson, [May 1862?]
- Letter. H. M. Anderson, Williamsburg to Maj. General Dix. Reports seizure of wine from her house, 13 September 1862.
- Letter. S. E. Smith to Mrs. Anderson. Reports that her liquor has been transferred to the Insane Asylum for safekeeping, 13 September 1862.
- Letter of Lt. W. John Simpson, Provost Marshall re liquor, 15 September 1862.
- Letter. Lt. Col S. E. Smith to Lt. Simpson, Provost Marshall, re furnishing Mrs. Anderson a guard for her house, 18 September 1862.
- Letter of Lt. Col. S. E. Smith re liquor in the possession of Mr. S. Moore, 18 September 1862.
- Account of the disposal of the wine stored at "the Eastern Lunatic Asylum." 20 September 1862.
- Note to send a bottle of wine. S. H. Bayley, Provost Marshall, Williamsburg to _______Flanigan, 27 September 1862.
- Note to send four bottles of wine. S. H. Bayley to Corp. Flanigan, 27 September 1862.
- Note to send six bottles of wine for medicinal purposes. Lt. S. Bayley, Williamsburg, to Corporal Flanigan, 27 September 1862.
- Note to send two bottles of wine. S. H. Bayley to Corp. Flanigan, 27 September 1862.
- Note to send a bottle of wine. S. H. Bayley to Corp. Flanigan, 27 September 1862.
- 28 September [1862]
- Note probably from Helen M. Anderson asking Lt. Col. Smith to send a letter to General Dix, [September 1862]
- Letter [Helen M. Anderson] to Capt. Hennessy re seizure of wine by soldiers, [September 1862]
- Note to send wine. Lt. W. John Simpson to Corp. Flanigan, [September 1862]
- Note to send wine. S. Bayley to Corp. Flanigan, [September 1862]
- Letter re wine. Helen M. Anderson to Capt. Hennessy, Provost, 3 October 1862.
- Will of Robert S. Bright, June 1912.
- Autobiographical essay of Robert A. Bright, n.d.
- 2 envelopes, n.d.